ILGWU Operations Department Industrial Homework Records 5780/196
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Operations Department Industrial Homework Records
1986-1989
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/196
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Contains reports, comments, testimonies, and statements submitted by the ILGWU and other interested organizations and individuals concerning revisions to the federal regulation of employment of homeworkers in certain industries, proposed between 1986 and 1989.
6180126
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 23, 2008
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 16, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Little documentation exists in the ILGWU records about the work of the Operations Department in the union's international offices, and the materials that comprise the Operations Department records do not explicitly show that they were created by the department per se. While typically an operations department is known to deal with the everyday business of an organization and to have responsibility for the organization's facilities, the records suggest that the department either complemented the work of the Research Department, the Master Agreements Department, and the former Management Engineering Department, or maintained records useful to those departments.
Scope and Contents
The Operations Department records consist materials relating to the ILGWU's efforts to maintain a ban on industrial homework, manuals for operations standards in the manufacturing of women's blouses and women's skirts, and collective bargaining agreements. The records relating to homework and operations standards date from the 1980s, and the collective bargaining agreements are from the years just before the ILGWU merged with ACTWU in 1995.
Researchers interested in ILGWU statements on homework and related issues should consult the Research Department records, 5780/209. Likewise, researchers looking for additional collective bargaining agreements should consult collections in Series VI, Contracts and Case Files (5780/075, 5780/075 mf, 5780/145, 5780/146, 5780/147, 5780/158, 5780/191). These records, and others throughout the ILGWU records, complement the records of the Operations Department.
In 1942, federal regulators prohibited homework in five industries--gloves and mittens, embroideries, buttons and buckles, handkerchiefs and jewelry production, as it was difficult to enforce federal wage and hour laws for work done in the home. After forty-five years, the ban was lifted, and this collection documents the ILGWU efforts to block the new homework rules. The collection contains reports, comments, testimonies, and statements submitted by the ILGWU and other interested organizations and individuals concerning revisions to the federal regulation of employment of homeworkers in certain industries, proposed between 1986 and 1989.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780/196: ILGWU Operations Department Industrial Homework Records 5780/202: ILGWU Operations Department Collective Bargaining Agreements 5780/202 PUBS: ILGWU Operations Department Publications Operations Standards Manuals
Home labor; Women's clothing industry; Abrams, Robert; Bencosme, Ana; Beyer, Dorianne; Bradley, Bill; Briggs, Vernon M.; Chew, Fay; Cleary, Edward J.(Edward John), 1906-; Davie, Fred; Elias, Eli; Guggenheimer, Elinor; Harris, James, 1948-; Herbert, Robin; Landrigan, Philip J.; Mazur, Jay; McDaid, Hugh; Muravchik, Miriam; Owens, R.; Snow, James F.; Snyder, Michelle; Wang, Charles P.; United States. Dept. of Labor
6180126
- Weintraub Report., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- ILGWU. Comments on Industrial Homework., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- ILGWU. Comments on Industrial Homework. Attachments, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- ILGWU. Comments on Industrial Homework. Supplemental, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- ILGWU. Comments on Industrial Homework. Supplemental. Attachments, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Statement by AFL-CIO Executive Council on Industrial Homework. Draft, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Public Hearing Agenda. Industrial Homework in the Women's Apparel Industry., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Robert Abrams Testimony., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ana Bencosme Testimony., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Dorianne Beyer Testimony., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Bill Bradley Testimony., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Vernon M. Briggs Jr. Testimony., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Fay Chew Statement., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Edward J. Cleary Testimony., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Fred Davie Jr. Testimony., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Eli Elias Testimony., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- James Harris Statement., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Robin Herbert Testimony., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Elinor Guggenheimer Testimony., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Philip J. Landrigan Testimony., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Jay Mazur Testimony., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Hugh McDaid Statement., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Miriam Muravchik Statement., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Major R. Owens Statement., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- James F. Snow Statement., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Michelle Snyder Statement., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Michelle Snyder Testimony., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Charles P. Wang Testimony., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- U.S. Department of Labor. Industrial Homework in the Women's Apparel Industry. Report, part 1., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- U.S. Department of Labor. Industrial Homework in the Women's Apparel Industry. Report, part 2., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- ILGWU. Comments on Industrial Homework., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Washington Post. Homework Ban Lifted Despite Warning. Clipping., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 32)